[SPEAKER_00]: Anurāḍa Sutta, he said, he's asking, what is the exalted deliverance of mind and what is the immeasurable deliverance of mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: An exalted, here it bequeathed by and resolved upon an area the size of the roots of one tree, pervading it as exalted.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is called an exalted deliverance of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he goes on further, two or three trees,
[SPEAKER_01]: The point being, even the smallest, as a root of a tree, basically, you start exalting your mind, literally, on the phenomenon that's larger than your body, that is present right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Larger than your body, but related to your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just through your body being seated at the root of the tree, but also being composed of four great elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not here to exalt your mind to the casinos of earth and so on, but it's enough just a room, just a floor that's wider than you, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, kuti.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kuti.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, if you make it personal, if you see that that kuti is composed of the four great elements that compose this very body, because of which you can think, feel, intend, decide, just do anything, well, because of which you exist, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you recognize, yeah, the kuti or the root of the tree, it will come to destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will come to a deformation.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is to be said for this body that's inferior to that?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's going to happen even sooner, even quicker.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just the knowledge of that, you don't have to then destroy the tree to prove it to yourself, or destroy this body to prove it to yourself, which would be a contradiction in terms, obviously, but just the knowledge that it's a subject to destruction, that pertains to you, to your body, to your center, to the center of your world, which is this physical body, it's enough for dispassion and for not regarding that body as yours, not taking it up, not appropriating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's also a kind of, well, also a kind of training to enlarge in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, to establish it on a greater phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I've seen two different things at once.
[SPEAKER_01]: What establishment is?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean you just start thinking about the roots of the trees or villages.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means there has to be that dependence established, that connection between the presence of the phenomenon of the greater kind
[SPEAKER_01]: In relation to the phenomenon of this body right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not just enough to think about mountains and elements or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to think it in relation to this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is the relation?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the simultaneous presence of these very four great elements that are comprising all these mountains, all these trees, this whole country, this church, including this body, these senses, these fleshy organs, because of which I am that which I think I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of that, my whole world can be swept away and it is undermined through a simple possibility of being swept away by these great elements, by the matter that's out of your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that changes, if that decides, if your heart decides to stop, for whatever reason, you don't know what's floating around your veins, you might block it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just, like, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, even these things that pertain to your body would be enough
[SPEAKER_01]: To recognize that you have absolutely no say in the operation of the organs and the fleshy senses, sense organs, because yet your whole world is known as your world because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when they go, your world cannot remain, not even for a second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, like, you can establish your mind on those greater things, like, say,
[SPEAKER_00]: Me walking in the village, me in the village surrounded by the mountains, and so on, and have that mountain range as my... as far as my body is going, while I'm not losing sight of my body, my situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's simultaneously present within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... it's not one and two.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like one within one.
[SPEAKER_01]: But do I have to think about that?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to think about it when the mind is not established upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the mind gets established upon it, because it's through... look, your body is within that, which means, through your body, you can see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, your body, the presence of the elements of your body, keep your mind established upon the greater
[SPEAKER_01]: phenomenon of those elements, which is the mountains, which is the mountain range, which is the... or on the other side, there's the perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind is established in that, because forest is greater than the little village.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your mind is established upon the perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you go in a village, nothing can beset you there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, it needs to be made personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not an abstract pondering on, you know, the composition of the rocks or the mountain range or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically seeing your body within that and seeing that through your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense, on top of the mountain range, there are trees being being swung by the wind, there's rolling rocks, there are, I don't know, crumbling dust of soil or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a more particular level, dead elements, yeah, your nails are growing, your body's moving around, you're sweating.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rising of the water in the river.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rising the water of the river, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Passing the water out from your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just...
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the elements moving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start seeing your body as pertaining to that, that will result eventually in you not regarding your body as pertaining to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I was...
[SPEAKER_00]: I wasn't really going into that contemplation, that kind of contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was more...
[SPEAKER_00]: Just expanding the mind for my body there, around it, within this, you know, as far as it's going.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is to learn how to keep seeing it within your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're moving, as that sutta says, when you establish the mind upon the perception of the forest, when you go into the village and you see sights, you see things that would usually provoke lust or anger or so on, you wouldn't, because the mind remains established upon the perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't want to have to just, oh, I must sit motionless, cross-legged, for three hours, to practice this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might start like that, without distractions, but the point of that establishment is to disregard your body, regardless of the posture, regardless of its activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just to have the establishment when you're seated and motionless, because that wouldn't be really an establishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when your body is seated, lying down, standing up, or walking, the mind remains established upon the Great Phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically your body is within that already.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the discernment that your body is already within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to fabricate anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to discern it right now, because it is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, it's the actual sutta after that, uh, upakālī, mārjupakālī.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha's questioning Anuradha, and he says, eh... how do you abide in meditation?
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, Venerable Sir, as we abide here, diligent, ardent, resolute, we perceive both light and a vision of forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Soon afterwards, the light and the vision of forms disappear, but we have not discovered the cause for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, I remember that being listed there, and
[SPEAKER_01]: There are lots of notes on Pāli.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that translation, which you're reading out now, has quite a good chance of being very subject to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to get a few different translations, the actual Pāli as well, and then work on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But go on, read the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha replies, you should discover the cause for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, before my enlightenment, while I was still only an unenlightened bodhisattva, I too perceived both lights and a vision of forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Soon after the light and the vision of forms disappeared, I thought, what is the cause and condition why the light and the vision of forms have disappeared?
[SPEAKER_00]: And I considered thus doubts arose in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, sometimes, he says, he sees... they see just light, and it just forms both
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it's like the whole light and thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Light and thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what is the parliament?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who has to stand there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, I mean, you know, he was translating, what was it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-indicative consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: The concept of non-indicative, I recall.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was translating consciousness that it's luminous all around.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what did that mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when it comes to this thing of lights and visions or forms, I think there might be different connotations that would probably make more sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I'm saying you have to look at all of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems that you can see separation, you can see forms, you can see light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in a way, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any form of
[SPEAKER_01]: Manifestation of phenomenon, even as a thought, requires its... well, its arising, its manifestation, which means there is a degree of light in it, in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if there is no degree of light in regard to it, Jesus would not be discerned against... against the nothingness, against basically non-arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you think about, like, I don't know, something like fleeting movements, just movements, just nothing particular, but thoughts that ponder on the nature...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that is discerned, to an extent, to a very ambiguous extent, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not clearly defined as the object of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as I said before, no matter how remote these thoughts are, they are valid phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, they have arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, there is a degree of light in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's... Like, if your mind were to be established upon the degree of light in regards to anything and everything that arises, means you'd be established in regards to everything and anything that arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very similarly, the Buddha did say that the ultimate, the highest of the all kāsinas is kāsina of consciousness, which is kāsina of a non- arising in regard to the arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of that... sorry, it's because of it that the arising is possible to be discerned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, consciousness is the ultimate negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're always conscious of, or rather, things are conscious of.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean when I say consciousness is out there with a form.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean it's... it's actually there like the form.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a completely separate, different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's out there paired with that form on the same... well, on the same level that it's below your feet.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive entering it, or even thinking about it, because whatever you think, you're already conscious of.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you're able to think it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means consciousness and the matter, in regard to it, are kind of prerequisites.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you say...
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, okay, think about darkness.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is an element of light in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're referring to that kind of... Yeah, that's very subtle, but imagine your mind gets
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, imagine, because through imagination, along the right lines, you will start getting a clearer picture, which means you will be able... well, it means your thoughts will be less and less of an abstraction, as we spoke before, and will become more valid representations of what it actually is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how this sermon happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the mind, as I said, imagining the mind is
[SPEAKER_01]: They were composed to such extent, the discernment of light in regard to things that have manifested, that are enduring, already manifested, just among anything that arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in a way, that all of that is because of that light in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, obviously, the light, in regard to it, will not be discerned, if there is nothing that this light is shining on, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, no, I don't like that, because it implies the direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, people think, ah, the shining light.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: The light will not be discerned, because the things that arise, well, will not reveal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thus, you will know there's light.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no light without the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't start assuming that the light is eternal and things are just being revealed by this massive torch.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Light is to the extent of the things arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not the things arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it actually belongs to things more than it belongs to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, completely belongs to things.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense that matter is paired with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not paired with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Matter is paired with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... it's not... it's not even that the matter is conscious, or consciousness possesses matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's just matter-consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two entirely separate entities that are juxtaposed together.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of that juxtaposition, you have
[SPEAKER_01]: Your whole life, your whole experience of everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that's why I mean there's always below your feet.
[SPEAKER_01]: That juxtaposition, that's the ratio between matter and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, well, you can't even think it accurately.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, the only way to think it accurately is to stop assuming it entirely.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were saying about, talking about movement, tension, movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's another word for it, intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, light, movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because everything has a movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indriya is everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, just even the nature of duration, like something is
[SPEAKER_01]: It's taking time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something is enduring in time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already a form of movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, that movement is the nature of intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is what intention is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's the most... it's the easiest to appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: It moves.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it also stands for the sense of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you are... you are molding it, applying it, applying it, withdrawing it, moving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, I am doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the movement,
[SPEAKER_01]: In itself, it's a phenomenon that's indifferent to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be there without you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, oh, I can't even control that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even my own intentions, the nature of those intentions, cannot be my own.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the easiest to purpose, easiest to take.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, in a way, the movement is also negative in regard to
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that move.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have solid objects, immovable objects, so to speak, that then they move.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we spoke before, you throw a cup.
[SPEAKER_01]: The movement, it's not the cup, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, there wouldn't be a movement of the cup if there is no discernible phenomenon of a solid, immovable cup.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say immovable, I mean immovable in itself, not immovable as a whole, that you can move from point A to point B.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the nature of the movement is not the things that move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Movement is not the things that move.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, there would be no movement if there's nothing to be moved.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the movement depends on things that can move.
[SPEAKER_01]: And things that can move, well, they're determined as things that determine the movement because they can move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the... if the cup suddenly starts moving, it melts away, ceases to be the cup.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, obviously, now you have this melted steel of this metal cup.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, now, that becomes a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is kind of a bit more movable, but even that movement in regard to the matter of that thing, the matter, is not movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there wouldn't be no movement, it has no matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just think.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, the planes of movement, the possibility of movement, is already given to you beforehand by that relationship, by that external relationship of matter and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you disown the movement as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The most personal of the intentions, choices, intentional intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the primary movement you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You attend this on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You move from that to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You choose to stay with that, which means you keep moving back to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that thing is enduring because it holds your interest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, when people's minds are all over the place, when they can't keep their attention, it's just... the movement is just... they're so weak, the mind is just flying everywhere, and they're moved with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that possibility of the movement, it's possible only because it is matter that's buried in consciousness, out there, external to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the planes of the movement, the space, the element of space, is already revealed to you as a result of that external relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, yeah, of course, yeah, yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why space, although it's not, like, the fundamental, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: element, in terms of the four great elements, is sometimes listed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, there's like four great elements and then it's listed as earth, water, fire, air, space and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the six elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I'm talking about when I say the external relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: The external relationship, or the earth, water, fire, air, juxtaposed with consciousness, results, or rather generates, the phenomenon of space within which movement is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind gets established upon the phenomenon of space,
[SPEAKER_01]: Means nothing that moves within that space can be appropriated, because you're established upon the greater phenomenon within which these things occur.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, as we spoke before, you're established upon the phenomenon of these great mountains you live on, and then whatever happens to you is within the presence of the mountains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sannyāsa, sorrow, grief, joy, elation, pertains to this tiny, little, insignificant body within this great notion of space.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a valid notion of space, not kind of, sort of, projected, mystical, whatever else, spaciousness, I don't want to call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The notion of space that is present within which this movement is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Movement reveals the space.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that move reveal...
[SPEAKER_01]: Things in space move.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, movement in regard to things, basically, it's what the intention is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, things are intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibilities, that's already a form of movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibilities are the same as thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have a cup, you can use it to drink from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the mind... that's already... mind already made a movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if you decide to use it for drinking, then you made a movement on top of the movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even the still possibility of a cup to be drank from, then it already implies the direction that now can be followed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has everything to do with the cup as an arisen phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you can intend to follow what has been given as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: So to watch movements, to watch...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you establish a mind upon the nature of the movement, there won't be movement, which means you won't be affected by anything that moves.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty much everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, the metaphor of immovable, in regard to everything, because you're surmounted by the nature of movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what has nature to move?
[SPEAKER_01]: Form has a nature to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling has a nature to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception has a nature to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentions, determinations, saṅkharas have a nature to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness has a nature to move.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that appears...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that, no matter how vaguely, how remotely, how ambiguously, might appear, to that extent, it moves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, even just pure, in the early commas, arising, ceasing, persisting, while changing, enduring, that's already a movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: A notion of time is a movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of the movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your thoughts, your feelings, your intentions, your perceptions, by arising, by ceasing, by persisting, while changing, by adhering, it's already movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's moving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind gets established upon the nature of movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing that particularly moves will be able to affect you, because the movement was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, in order to establish your mind upon that, that movement needs to be taken personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Needs to be pertaining to that which you take to be yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Needs to be determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: Needs to be bound by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, by disowning the movement, then you will be unable to hold this thing to be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perception, feeling, you can describe the feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can feel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... and there's movement in regard to it, which is where your intention is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, your attention in regard to feelings moves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but feelings... feelings... Yeah, they endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: They persist.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a movement discerned there.
[SPEAKER_01]: More general movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, the most particular movement, the one that's
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, even if your mind is moving around, jumping around, you can be quite a stubbish, because
[SPEAKER_01]: If your intention is to... Yeah, because you are not being moved by the jumping mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because you're paying... Can you pay attention to attention?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can't be attending your attention, but you can certainly discern the roots of your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your attention has to direct itself at something, but that doesn't mean that your whole vision has to be taken with that 100%.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, by attending something, you can remain aware of the background of that attention that's attending this particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's nothing, then, developing yoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The root, the womb of your attention, where the... where the... where the attention comes from, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by remaining mindful, established, discerning,
[SPEAKER_01]: The background, in regards to that which is being attended to, you're getting the whole... the picture of the whole direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole direction of the movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by dwelling, or rather by discerning sufficiently enough, the whole direction of the movement, you realize that there is no room for your sense of self in that movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only because movement, it's easy to ignore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, movement becomes my movement, the movement of me, the symbol that stands for my sense of control, for mine, for my appropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it moves.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's easiest to ignore, not see.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I've reached up, I just sank down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that ignoring,
[SPEAKER_01]: That movement becomes the determination of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, one thing I always, you know, Vera says, Maitre Dhamma, intentions may be regarded basically as the relation between the actual and the possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The relationship between the actual and the possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: In what we're just talking about now,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, movement is determined by the possibility of things to be moved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, Nainavidya is also talking about space.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that specifically,
[SPEAKER_01]: But, talking about the intentions, if there is the presence of the intention, they basically correlate to the notion of space and the three dimensions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, that's with unnecessary detail, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, it ties in with what we just read.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, possibility of... and there is a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: are not that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're possible and there isn't things actual.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the possibilities are the directions that you can move that thing towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by thinking the possibilities, you're already moving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, the movement, the... oh, sorry, the thoughts, the intentions towards those possibilities are determined by possible and the actual and short.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the immeasurable deliverance of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is... what is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here Bhikkhu abides pervading one quarter, the mind imbued with loving-kindness, likewise the second, likewise the third, fourth, above, below, around and everywhere, as to all as to himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he... he establishes mind... his mind on
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of saying, you know, metta, kindness, dharmic kindness, he could establish his mind on non-ill-will, or... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-merits.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it compassion, uncruelty, or something?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I think we spoke about it before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, that's probably why we're mentioning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, non-ill-will is greater than ill-will, because ill-will is always in regard to particular things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so, it says here, you get a full-blown mirage, loving-kindness, compassion, altruistic joy, and equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it says, abundant, exalted, immeasurable, and always says, without hostility and without ill-will, you bind to the mind, loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But can't you just abide with a mind of money or will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that he doesn't generate a mind of kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not intentionally, as people think you should do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's generated indirectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through establishing your mind in non-hostility and non-ill-will, if you establish yourself long enough for a sufficient degree in that, the result, that experience, what you experience at the time, is the experience of loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Between the experience of loving-kindness is determined by your establishment upon non-hostility and non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can't appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha did praise Brahmā Mihārās, and they can lead you to arahantship and full destruction of the fetters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, in as much like jhānas, you can't appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: I am feeling matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: There wouldn't be matter, if there is a sense of self in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your sense of self is concerned about no hostility, no ill will, and it sticks to that, then eventually becomes redundant, and the result of that is the experience of loving kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can intend it, you can, whatever, build on top of that, go further, and it all eventually results in equanimity, immovable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, yeah, that's why it's quite...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's quite dangerous anyway, because people read Brahmavihārās and you think, oh, now I just have to start thinking positive thoughts, good thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can think that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But don't think that that is the practice of Brahmavihārās, because then you will never make the effort to find out what the actual practice of Brahmavihārās really is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can know that whatever you're doing is not the practice of Brahmavihārās, because you're not an ārahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were to do it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even that long, it would result, if you don't do it correctly, it would result in destruction of all fetters, because it undermines the very framework of the sense of self, in regard to me, in regard to others, in regard to both, in regard to neither.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no room for self in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, there's no room for self in jhānas, which is why brahmicāras can also be used to then establish a mind into a jhāna upon them, depending how you start intending to things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize without his mind, without hostility and without ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as you're saying, ill-will is... non-ill-will is a greater phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And ill-will is much smaller, much more particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it needs to be particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have ill-will in the general manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even then, if you're like generally bad mood, well, that becomes a particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ill-will is always directional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, non-near-will is always greater.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always the basis of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if someone was... someone was abiding, most of the time, in non-near-will, or attending to that phenomenon, and they get angry, but they can't really get angry that much... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the displeasing, the disagreeable circumstances, if their mind is established,
[SPEAKER_01]: If they dwell often, as the Buddha said, you should dwell often in these states, then they will kind of rise.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically like like heating the pan.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the pan is just mildly warm, when you throw the water, well, the water will linger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But imagine you keep warming up that pan for quite some time and it's red hot.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how much water you chuck on it, it will just immediately evaporate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wouldn't linger at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you know, you get careless, the fire drops down, cools down, then even a tiny drop of water will linger a long time, if it's a cold pan.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same with the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind doesn't dwell upon, like, the phenomena, the notions, the abstractions of non-ill-will, just think abstractly what it is to have non-malice and non-hostility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwell on that long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't actively try to love people or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already particularizing of that thing, which is a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result of non-hostility, non-ill-will, will be a genuine loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: A loving-kindness that doesn't induce the sense of self, that doesn't induce the sense of conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Loving-kindness is just a pure framework of me and others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither of us can really own what we think we own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you just have loving-kindness and compassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Compassion to the kind of indifferent framework of your experience as it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't, or rather, you can get that directly through this indirect practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the, in a way, in itself, on its own, it's a direct way, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not a direct way from what people think it's a direct way.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am spreading beams of loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's never been a point enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are radiating beams of loving-kindness,
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you do then, when it comes to upāyaka?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you radiate beams of indifference?
[SPEAKER_01]: How does that work?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sending you the beams of my equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm moving these beams towards you of this immovability.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just nonsense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's always a painful practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contrived.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a very contrived practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't always seem inadequate, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very adequate if it's done rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: Almost effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all you have to do is pay attention and make sure non-ill will, non-hostility prevails.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you have to do is guard the gates, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more fortified those gates are, the less things will be going through of ill-will and hostility.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when that becomes a state you abide in, often enough, that's your brahmavihāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result is metta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mudita, karuṇa, and then just complete, immovable, indriyātula.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because metta, mudita, karuṇa are the subtle movements.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're so subtle, so neutral, that any of them can be a base for the full destruction of fetters and other energy, which then results in equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inasmuch, you need only one first jhāna to dwell in it sufficiently enough, abide in it, and then all the fetters will fall off and you'll be all right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need the actual jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need the strength of the mind that pertains to the actual first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can have different means of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can arrive at adhārāṇaship through bhagavad-gītā, even if you never thought about or heard about jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just a form of establishment of your mind, a way you can establish your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when Buddha says, oh, you need the first jhāna as a basis for the destruction of things, means you need that strength of mind that corresponds to the first jhāna, which would correspond, you know, to various other things as well, but they were talking about jhānas at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it does seem to suggest, in the sūtra as well, that if you're... if you are... if there's defilements, you can still establish your mind on these... on nānyā world, but you might have other defilements coming up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But your mind still can be established.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the better you get, the more... the more established it gets, the less lingering defilements will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and he's obviously talking about... if someone's doing that and they got... it's like the... he gave you born into a... what is it... pure birds of pure... Yeah, quite subtle realms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've got very mild radiance or the pure radiance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're measurable radiance or limited radiance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it depends on how strong you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depends on how often your mind was abiding in those refined... well... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Relatively refined states.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're refined from the practitioner's point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... yeah, if your mind starts abiding in non-facilitating, non-ill will get established upon brahma-vihāras.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your abiding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your state.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you still perceive, oh, this is more refined than what I used to do, what I used to think, what I used to feel, eh... but now it's the state that you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now you can recognize, oh, there is... You know, when the Sariputta thinks about jhānas and says, it gets established in this and it's great and mindfulness... Is there more?
[SPEAKER_01]: There is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you get the principle out of it, fully develop it, and you'll be an Arhat, then you can go wherever you want to go or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if somebody doesn't become an Arhat, but abides in those states, then the Buddha did say,
[SPEAKER_01]: These realms of rebirth correspond to abiding in those mental states, which is consequently abiding in the mental states that are infused with lust, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what corresponds to that is the annular realm, if you're lucky.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I'm going to read this, God actually could be reborn in these god realms.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, unfortunately, you never think of...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a duration.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pleasurable, but it's still... you have to go through with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it still comes to an end.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wonder if your... your efforts towards... arahantship is wasted.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you get reborn in this karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your efforts to nibbāna cannot possibly waste it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you become... like that's how sometimes people over a course of lifetimes build up enough and then they become arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all the efforts from previous lives, toil and up always, nothing can go to waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sensuality goes to waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your will goes to waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance goes to waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any effort made to uproot those cannot possibly go to waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not get the immediate result, but it's like, again, like a drop, drop, drop in the ocean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bit by bit by bit by bit by bit, you fill up the entire ocean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what usually happens, based on the suttas, when people, they pass away, but they met the previous Buddha, and they obviously got inspired, made offerings,
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it seems like great, man.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get all this pleasure and then become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The greatest pleasure is to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you're delaying your pleasure through being reborn in these celestial realms.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can last for years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Goodness me!
[SPEAKER_01]: For years!
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... you don't know what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Better than nothing is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Better than nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Better than animal realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: But still.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if the efforts were genuinely aiming at nibbāna, that cannot go to waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it would have meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you cultivate the right view for a finger snap, if you cultivate loving-kindness for a finger snap, that's how you make streams of merit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because merit pertains to the future benefits of your present action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through applying yourself... Like, you make merit through giving and offering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's nothing in comparison to merit that you get through having a finger snap of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Finger snap of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Finger snap of brahmavihāyas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to, you know, you need to have the finger snap of the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I want to qualify that, because then, you know, you do have people as well, as long as I'm trying, I'll make merit and I'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're trying the wrong thing, if you're following the wrong teachings, if you're following things that cannot lead to understanding, well, you don't have the finger snap, even a finger snap of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not easy, but if it's done, even those fleeting moments of the right view of this stream of magic, which means, yeah, exactly that, in the future, lots of benefits from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone could say that most people abide in non-real world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but not...
[SPEAKER_00]: Most of the time I'm upset a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, right, except when I'm not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Except when I'm not.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you know... Oh, I keep the precepts, except when I don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's nothing in comparison to the time I spend keeping the precepts, thus my precepts are much greater.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: My mind is not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not getting angry or anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but there is a difference in... in knowing libido in your will and being delusional about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you know what the phenomenon of ill-will is?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you possibly be abiding in it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're abiding in delusion, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your mind is where your ill-will is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that that ill-will is not always present.
[SPEAKER_01]: But delusion certainly is, which is why, on the basis of that delusion, you can have ill-will arising, you can have hostility, lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why delusion is the most fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: For all of the unwholesome states, it's the basis from which they spring out.